<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The compassionate Samaritane unbinding the conscience, and powring oyle into the wounds which have beene made upon the separation: recommending their future welfare to the serious thoughts, and carefull endeavours of all who love the peace and unity of Commonwealths men, or desire the unanimous prosecution of the common enemie, or who follow our Saviours rule, to doe unto others, what they would have others doe unto them.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W681B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1202_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208770</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867692</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120014</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97096)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120014)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 168:E1202[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The compassionate Samaritane unbinding the conscience, and powring oyle into the wounds which have beene made upon the separation: recommending their future welfare to the serious thoughts, and carefull endeavours of all who love the peace and unity of Commonwealths men, or desire the unanimous prosecution of the common enemie, or who follow our Saviours rule, to doe unto others, what they would have others doe unto them.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
                  <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, corrected, and enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[10], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. By William Walwyn. Sometimes also attributed to John Goodwin.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 5th"; "London"; caret after 'and' in edition statement and "much" written above line.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120014:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Compaſſionate SAMARITANE <hi>Vnbinding</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſcience, and powring Oyle into the wounds which have been made upon the <hi>Separation:</hi> recommending their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture welfare to the ſerious thoughts, and carefull endeavours of all who love the peace and vnity of Commonwealths men, or deſire the vnanimous proſecution of the Common Enemie, or who follow our Saviours rule, to <hi>doe unto others, what they would have others doe unto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second <hi>Edition,</hi> corrected, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged. <hi>Printed in the Yeare 1644.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:120014:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Si populus vult decipi, decipiatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:120014:2"/>
            <p>To him that reads.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>IF after this, when all the guiles,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That have miſled you, and the wiles</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are manifeſted cleare as day,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So that you muſt ſay,</hi> theſe are they:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You yet will be befoold, you may.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Errours have ſome excuſe, when theyr not knowne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But being known once, wilfulneſſe has none.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:120014:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:120014:3"/>
            <head>TO THE COMMONS OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>TO You whom the Peolpe have choſen for the managing of their affaires, I preſent this neceſſary Treatiſe without boldneſſe and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare: for I am well aſſured, that as it is mine, and every mans duty, to to furniſh You with what we conceive will advance the Common good, or bring eaſe or comfort to any ſort of men that deſerve well of their Countrey (as You cannot but know the <hi>Seperation</hi> doe, if You conſider with what charge
<pb facs="tcp:120014:4"/> and hazard, with what willingnes and activity they have furthered the Reformation ſo happily begun) ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is, Your duty, to heare and put in execution, whatſoever to Your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall appeare conducing to thoſe good ends and purpoſes. I recommend here to Your vew the oppreſſed <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and the deſpiſed <hi>Separation:</hi> They have been much wounded (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive every body can ſay by whom) and the people have paſſed by without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion or regard, though they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves muſt neceſſarily partake in their ſufferings There are none left, to play the <hi>good Samaritanes</hi> part but Your ſelves, who as You have power; will, (I make no queſtion) be willing too, when You have once well conſidered the matter, which this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe</hi> will put You in mind to doe. It is not to be ſuppoſed, that You (who have ſo long ſpent Your time in recovering
<pb facs="tcp:120014:4"/> the <hi>Common Liberties</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould in Concluſion turne the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> into <hi>Particular;</hi> let the inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations and ſuggeſtions of ſome in the <hi>Synod,</hi> be what they will, I make no queſtion, but You will ſee both through and beyond them; and will never be ſwayed from a good conſcience to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine particular mens Intereſts.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of Your <hi>Seſſion,</hi> when our <hi>Divines</hi> (as they would have us call them) wrote freely againſt the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Biſhops</hi> made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to You for redreſſe; ſome of You made anſwer, that there was no reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, foraſmuch as <hi>the Preſſe was to be open and free for all in time of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament:</hi> I ſhall make bold as a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to lay claime to that <hi>priviledge,</hi> being aſſured that I write nothing ſcandalous, or dangerous to the <hi>State,</hi> (which is juſtly and vpon good grounds prohibited by Your <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:120014:5"/> to that effect) only I humbly deſire You to conſider whether more was not got from You by that <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> then You intended, and that though it was purpoſed by You to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the venting and diſperſing of the <hi>Kings</hi> writings and his Agents, yet it hath by reaſon of the qualifications of the <hi>Licenſers</hi> wrought a wrong way, and ſtopt the mouthes of good men, who muſt either not write at all, or no more then is ſutable to the judgments and intereſts of the <hi>Licencers.</hi> The <hi>Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> (I gueſſe) would have tooke it for be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter dealing, if the <hi>Divines</hi> had in expreſſe tearmes obtained of You an <hi>Ordinance</hi> for ſuppreſſion of all <hi>Anabaptiſticall, Browniſticall,</hi> or <hi>Independant</hi> writings; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have their mouthes ſtopt ſubtlely, ſo inſenſibly, and their <hi>juſt Liberty</hi> in time of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> taken from them vnawares. There can be no greater Argument, that
<pb facs="tcp:120014:5"/> the <hi>Divines</hi> intend not well, than their taking uncough, and myſterious, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile wayes to effect their ends; even ſuch as far better become <hi>Polititians,</hi> then <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is high time O <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to put an End to the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the <hi>Seperation,</hi> who have for many yeares been the object of all kind of tyranny, Papiſticall, Prelaticall, and Regall: The firſt Foundation of honor, and reſpect was certainly from publike ſervice and protection of the diſtreſſed: Make it Your worke, and aſſure Your ſelves, You will find not only the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall love of all good men accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning You, but a quiet and cheerfull Conſcience, which is above all honour and riches, Others may weary them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in plots and contrivances to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance ſelfe-ends and intereſts, to the peoples dammage and moleſtations; ſadneſſe and diſtraction will be their
<pb facs="tcp:120014:6"/> companions for it. But make it Your buſineſſe, Ye <hi>choſen men</hi> of <hi>England</hi> according to the truſt rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed in You to protect, he Innocent, to judg their cauſe impartially, to circunmvent men in their wicked endeavours; and ſo You will become the beloved of God, the beloved of good men.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120014:6"/>
            <head>LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE ASSERTED, And the Separatiſt vindicated.</head>
            <p>HAving heretofore met with an Apologeticall Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Thomas Goodwin, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Nye, Sydrach Sympſon, Jeremy Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, William Bridge;</hi> I did with gladneſſe of heart undertake the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof, expecting therein to find ſuch generall reaſons for juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of themſelves, to the world, as would have juſtified all the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and ſo have removed by one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:120014:7"/> diſcourſe thoſe prejudices and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſions, which even good men have of that harmleſſe and well meaning ſort of people: But finding contrary to that expectation that their Apologie therin for them ſelves and their Toleration was grounded rather upon a Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the nearneſſe between them and the Presbyterian, being one in Doctrine with them, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little differing from them in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, how they had been tolerated by other Presbyter Churches, and indulgd with greater priviledges, then the Separatiſt, how they differed from the Separatiſt, and had cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly avoyded thoſe roks and ſhelves againſt which the Separatiſt had ſplit themſelves, confirming by theſe words, the peoples diſeſteem of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiſts, ſuggeſting by that phraſe of theirs, as if there were amongſt the Separatiſts ſome dangerous by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathes
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:120014:7"/> or opinions, which they wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſhund, though no mention be made what they are, which is the worſt ſort of calumny.</p>
            <p>Finding to my hearts greife the Seperatiſt thus left in the lurch, and likely to be expoſed to greater dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers then ever by the endeavours of theſe men, my heart abounded with greife, knowing the Innocency of their intentions, and honeſty of their lives, that they are neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to be of the mind they are, upon long examination of their owne te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents that they deſire nothing more then that they ſhould be publikely and impartially reaſoned, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing likewiſe their affection to the Common-wealth, their forwardnes of aſſiſtance in purſe and perſon, knowing eheir Meetings to be ſo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, ſo far from confederacy or counterplots (though they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120014:8"/> ſenſible of the ſad and perplexed condition that they are in) that they have not yet ſo much as ſpoke ought in their owne defence, but truſting to the goodneſſe of God, the equity of the Parliament, the ſimplicity and and integrity of their owne wayes, doe quietly enjoy themſelves and their worſhip, let what will be brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt them, being reſolved like <hi>Heſter</hi> to doe their dutyes, and if in doing thereof they periſh, they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: Me thinkes every man is bound in conſcience to ſpeak and doe what he can in the behalfe of ſuch a harmeleſſe people as theſe: what though you are no Separatiſt (as I my ſelfe am none) the love of God appeares moſt in doing good for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: that love which aimes only at it ſelfe; thoſe endeavours which would procure liberty only to them ſelves, can at beſt be called but ſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:120014:8"/> love and ſelfe reſpects: 'Tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon freedome every man ought to aime at, which is every mans pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar right ſo far as 'tis not prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to the Common: Now becauſe little can be done in their behalfe, unleſſe Liberty of Conſcience be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for every man, or ſort of men to worſhip God in that way, and performe Chriſts Ordinances in that manner as ſhall appear to them moſt agreeable to Gods Word, and no man be puniſhed or diſcountenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Authority for his Opinion, unleſſe it be dangerous to the State: I have endeavoured in this Diſcourſe to make appeare by the beſt reaſon I have, that every man ought to have Liberty of Conſcience of what Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſoever, with the caution above named: In doing whereof, I have upon occaſion removed all prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that the people have concerning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:120014:9"/> the Separatiſt, and vindicated them from thoſe falſe aſpertious that are uſually caſt upon them to make them odious; wherein, my end, I make account, will evidently appeare, to be the peace and vnion of all, and to beget this judgement in the People and Parliament, that 'tis the principall intereſt of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that Authority ſhould have equall reſpect, and afford protection to all peaceable good men alike, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their difference of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that all men may be encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be alikeſerviceable thereunto; liberty of Conſcience is to be allowed every man for theſe following reaſons</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Becauſe of what judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſoever a man is, he cannot chuſe but be of that judgement, that is ſo evident in it ſelfe, that I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it will be granted by all, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever a mans reaſon doth conclude
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:120014:9"/> to be true or falſe, to be agreeabe or diſagreabe to Gods Word, that ſame to that man is his opinion or judgement, and ſo man is by hisown reaſon neceſſitated to be of that mind he is, now where there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity there ought to be no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for puniſhment is the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of voluntary actions, therfore no man ought to be puniſhed for his judgment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> But it will be Objected, That the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts are a raſh, heady People, and not ſo much concluded by their Reaſon, as their Fancie, that they have their <hi>Enthuſiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> as, and Revelations, which no body knowes what to make off, and that if they were a people that examined things rationally, the Argument would hold good for them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:120014:10"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That I ſuppoſe this to be the Argument not of the preſent, but of looſe witted times before the Parliament, where ſome politike Biſhop, or Dr. Ignorant Univerſity man, or knave Poet would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by ſuch a ſuggeſtion to the people to miſguide their credulous hearts into hatred of thoſe good men, who they knew to be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant enemies to their deluſions: but let all men now have other thoughts, and aſſure themſelves that the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt and Anabaptiſt are rationall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminers of thoſe things they hold for truth, milde diſcourſeres, and abe to give an account of what they they beleive; they who are unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in that particular, may, if they pleaſe to viſite their private Congregations which are open to all commers, have further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; perhaps here and there amongſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120014:10"/> them may be a man that out of his zeale and earneſtnes for that which he eſteemes truth, may outrune his underſtanding, &amp; ſhew many weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes in his diſcourſe, I would the like frailty and inabilities were not to be found in many of us; but if the ſlips and wanderings of a few, and thoſe the weakeſt, be an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient to diſcountenance the Separation, and worke them out of the worlds favour, I pray God the ſame Argument may never be made vſe of againſt us; amongſt whom, many, and they not eſteemed the weakeſt neither, would give great advantages that way: In the mean time I wiſh with all my heart we could all put on the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and rather endeavour to rectifie by argument and perſwation one anothers infirmities, then upbraid the owners of them with a viſible
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120014:11"/> rejoycing that ſuch things are ſlipt from them to their diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>One Cuſtome they have amongſt them which doth make even the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of them able arguers in defence of their way, and that is either an uſe of objecting againſt any thing delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red amongſt them, or propoſing any doubt, whereof any deſires to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, which is done in a very or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly manner, by which meanes the weakeſt becomes in a ſhort time much improved, and every one able to give an account of their Tenets, (not relying upon their Paſtors, as moſt men in our congregations doe) which may ſerve to remove the objection, and put us to conſider, whether the like cuſtome be not wanting amongſt us.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> The uncertainty of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in this life: no man, nor no ſort of men can preſume of an uner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:120014:11"/> ſpirit: 'Tis knowne that the Fathers, Generall Councells, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Aſſemblies, Synods, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments in their times have been moſt gloſly miſtaken: and though the preſent times be wiſer then the former, being much freed from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and taking a larger liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to themſelves of examining all things, yet ſince there remaines a poſſibility of errour, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding never ſo great preſumptions of the contrary, one ſort of men are not to compell another, ſince this hazard is run thereby, that he who is in an errour, may be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainer of him who is in the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But unity and uniformity in Religion is to be aimed at, and confuſion above all things to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyded, by Toleration new Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120014:12"/> will every day breake forth, and to the ſcandall of the Nation, we ſhall become a very monſter in matters of Religion, one part being Presbyter, another Anabaptiſt, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt another, and a fourth an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, and ſo divers according to the diverſity of opinions that are already, or may be broached here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, that in truth this objection appeares ſpecious at the firſt gloſſe, and therfore is very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon the people, which the Biſhops well knew, whoſe it was, and taken up as the faireſt pretence for the ſuppreſſion of thoſe, who it is to be feared, will prove the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors. For anſwer whereunto I averre, that a compulſion is of all wayes the moſt unlikely to beget u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of mind, and vniformity in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120014:12"/> practice, which experience will make evident. For,</p>
            <p>The Fines, Impriſonments, Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lories, &amp;c. uſed by the Biſhops as meanes to unite, rather confirmed men in their judgments, and begot the abomination and <hi>odium</hi> which theſe times have caſt upon the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, being in the worſt kind ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall, as endeavouring by the puniſhment of the perſon, the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſubjecting of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And if it be it inſtanced, that ſome there were that turned with the wind, and were terrified by feare of puniſhment into a compliance. I anſwer, that ſuch men are ſo farre from being examples to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they may more juſtly be condemned for weather-cokes fit (to be ſet up for men to know which way blowes the wind) of favour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120014:13"/> delicacy, eaſe and preferment.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The conſcience being ſubject only to reaſon (either that which is indeed, or ſeems to him which hears it to beſo) can only be convinced or perſwaded thereby, force makes it runne backe, and ſtrugle; it is the nature of every man to be of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny judgment rather then his that forces. 'Tis to be preſumed, that tis upon ſome good grounds of reaſon that a man is of that Iudgement whereof he is. Would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou have him be of thine? ſhew him thy grounds, and let them both worke, and ſee which will get the victory in his underſtanding. Thus poſſibly he may change his mind, and be of one judgment with thee: but if you will uſe Club Law, inſtead of convincing and uniting, you arme men with prejudice againſt you, to conclude that you haue no aſſurance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120014:13"/> of truth in you, for then you would make uſe of that, and preſume of the efficacy thereof, and not fight with weapons which you (doe or at leaſt ſhould) know not to be the weapous of truth. But I feare there is ſomething more in it: I cannot thinke that the Biſhops in their times vſed ſo many ſtratagems of vexation and cruelty againſt good people, to gaine them to be of their mind, they could not be ignorant that they ſet the Nonconformiſts of all ſorts thereby at an irreconcilable hatred againſt them. No, there end rather was this, They had conſulted who were oppoſite to their deſignes, and finding the Puritane and Sectary ſo to be, their intereſt was by all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes to ſuppreſſe them, that ſo they might without oppoſition trample upon the people. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in theſe times men ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120014:14"/> what they doe. For if they who have the publique countenance doe beare them elves after the ſame manner towards the Anabaptiſts and Browniſts, or whatſoever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſect there is, or may be, that cannot comply with them in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or practice (as by their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings we feare they will) what can we judge of them but that their ends and intentions are the ſame with the Biſhops? For by their fruits (ſaith our Saviour) ye ſhall know them: we may be deceived by words their turnings and contextures are ſo inſinite, that they may be framed ſo, as to make the worſt ſeeme good. The actions of men are the beſt rules for others to judge them by. Now upon view of the actions of the Divines that are now in favour, men doe ſpeake very ſtrangly, ſome ſay the tyrannie over
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120014:14"/> conſcience that was exerciſed by the Biſhops, is like to be continued by the Presbiters: that the oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours are only changed, but the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion not likly to be removed. Others ſay, that the Anabaptiſt and Browniſt are like to find harder maſters, for that the Biſhops made the puniſhment of them a matter of ſport and profit to themſelves, and reſerved their puniſhments to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions of the peoples mindes from taking too much notice of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchments upon the lawes and common liberty, ſuffering their ſocieties notwithſtanding to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, though ſo low and deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that they were paſt feare of them. But the Presbiters, as it is conceived, will be more violent, as ſlaves uſually are when they become maſters: and thus talke not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Anabaptiſt and Browniſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:120014:15"/> and Antinomian (being cheifly in danger) but other the moſt mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ingenious meu, that are not ſwayed by the Divines intereſt.</p>
            <p>They ſay too, that as it is not juſt, ſo neither is it politike, that in the beginnings and firſt riſe, when the Divines are but laying the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their greatneſſe, wealth, and ſway over the peoples conſciences, and twiſting their intereſt inſenſibly with the Parliaments, that in the in fancy of their tyrannie they ſhould carry themſelves ſo high and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous as they doe over other men, ſhewes that their wiſedome here comes ſomewhat ſhort of the Serpents, or elſe that they are ſo impatient at the not compliance of other men, that they break, out e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt their owne intereſt. Nay ſome ſay further, that they did well indeed in being ſo zealous againſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120014:15"/> the Biſhops, thoſe Drones and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillers of the Commonwealth, in making deſervedly odious to the people their oppreſſive Courts? Fines, Cenſures, and Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But they begin to fear thatſome bad ends of their owne were aimed at herein, and not ſo much the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the people, as that they might get up into the Chaire and become to them inſtead of a Lord Biſhop, a ruling Presbytery, which they feare will bring in more rigid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and auſterity, no leſſe ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and domination then the former.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon they have to feare, is, becauſe our Divines have not dealt clearely with us in many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, but continue cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts of the Biſhops, which they find advantagious to advance their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; eſteeme with the people and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120014:16"/> have entered already into many of their ſteps, which in them at firſt they did ſeem ſo much to abomin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te. That the intereſt only of the Biſhop in particular, and of that ſort of Prelates is exploded; but the generall intereſts of the Clergie, whereby an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Prelacy may be erected, and the myſtery of the Divines maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in credit amongſt the people, is ſtill with all art and induſtry preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. I will take the paines both to tell you what thoſe generall intereſts are, and what in reaſon may be ſaid againſt them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Their firſt intereſt is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve amongſt the people the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction concerning Government of Ecclefiaſticall and Civill, though up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſideration it will be found that two Governments in one Common-wealth hath ever been, and will ever prove inconſiſtent with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120014:16"/> the peoples ſafety: The end of Government being to promote virtue, reſtraine vice, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to each particular his owne, one ſort of Government which we call the Civill, either is ſufficient, or by the wiſedome of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be made ſufficient for theſe ends. At the beginning of this Parliament it was confeſſed, that it was both too burdenſome for the Divines, and too bazardous for the State, that they ſhould bee truſted with any thing of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their preaching and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the people being, if well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, ſufficient to take up the whole man. But the times change, and the men with them; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne is feaſible, and it muſt now againe be thought neceſſary that the Divines ſhould have a ſtroake in the Government, and therefore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120014:17"/> that diſtinction is againe maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which being taken up at firſt by proud Church-men for ambitious ends, is ſtill continued for ends though not in every thing the ſame, yet differing (I feare me) rather in the degrees than nature of them, we cannot tell what elſe to thinke of it, but that finding our Divines aiming at authority and juriſdiction, have judged it moſt politicke to gaine a preheminence, (leſſe ſtately and pompous, but) altogether as impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and awfull over men as the former, which becauſe it is not ſo gariſh outwardly as the Biſhops, they may preſume will therefore be the eaſier admitted, and prove of longer continuance.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond intereſt of the Divine, is to preſerve amongſt the people the diſtinction of Clergie and Laity, though not now in thoſe termes, becauſe they have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120014:17"/> diſcovered. The Scriptures ſo evidently makeing the people Gods Clergy by way of diſtinction from the Miniſters, <hi>1 Pet. 5. 3.</hi> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Miniſters by way of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the people. And then for Laity, a people (as the word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies) I hope the Miniſters are ſuch as well as any others. Well, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction by words is not ſo materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as a reall diſtinction with their intereſt is to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve. They would not have us to thinke that a Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comes to be ſo, as an other man comes to be ſo, as an other man comes to be a Merchant, Bookeſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Taylor, &amp;c. either by diſpoſall of him by his friends in his educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by his owne making choyce to be of ſuch a Trade: no, there muſt be ſomething ſpirituall in the buſineſſe, a <hi>Iure Divino</hi> muſt be brought in, and a ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles, and even as ſome would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120014:18"/> have us thinke Kings to be annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, becauſe the Iſraelitiſh Kings were by his command, ſo we are made to beleive, that becauſe the Apoſtles were ordained by God to be Teachcers of the people, and endued with guifts for that end; that therefore there is a like divine, though ſecret ordination from God in making of our Miniſters, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall guifts &amp; qualifications there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: Becauſe otherwiſe, if the people did not beleive ſo, they would examine all that was ſaid, and not take things upon truſt from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as if whatſoever they ſpake, God ſpake in them: they would then try all things, and what they found to be truth, they would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace as from God, for God is the Authour of truth; what they found to be otherwiſe, they would reject, and then for the moſt part they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120014:18"/> might ſpare their nothings and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petions too, unleſſe the more to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the groundleſneſſe of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the giddineſſe of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the giddineſſe of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity which they generally heare. They would then handle their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters familiarly, as they doe one an other, ſhaking off that timorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and awe which they have of the Divines, with which they are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly brought up. He that bade us try all things, and hold faſt that which was good, did ſuppoſe that men have faculties and abilities wherewithall to try all things, or elſe the counſell had beene given in vaine. And therefore however the Miniſter may by reaſon of his continuall exerciſe in preaching, and diſcourſing, by his daily ſtudy, and reading, by his skill in Arts and Languages, by the conceit of the eſteeme he hath with a great
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:120014:19"/> part of admiring people (in whom is truly fulfilled the prophecie of St. <hi>Paul, 2 Tim.</hi> 4. 3. 4. ) preſume it eaſie to poſſeſſe us, that they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re divine then other men (as they ſtyle themſelves) yet if the people would but take boldnes to themſelves and not diſtruſt their owne underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, they would ſoon find that uſe and experience is the only difference, and that all neceſſary knowledge is eaſie to be had, and by themſelves acquirable: and that it is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters intereſt, their living depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereupon, to frame long me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and bodies of Divinity, full of doubts and diſputes, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are made of purpoſe difficult to attaine unto, that their hearers may be a lwyes learning, and never come to the knowledg of the trnth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting diſquiet and unſetledneſſe of mind, continuall controverſies, ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120014:19"/> and many times deſperation: All which makes for them, for that upon all occafionsmen have recourſe to them for comfort and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which how weake and ſhort ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be in it ſelfe, muſt be currant, becauſe from them: the Keyes of the Church (a prerogative which our Saviour gave to his Apoſtles, ) they arrogate to themſelves, a new Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they make mention of in their Sermons, which they call Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial (though no ſuch thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to them, nor is yet ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, nor I hope ever will be) thus their intereſt is to make of themſelves a peculiar Tribe, of a nearer relation to God then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men: His more immediate Servants the Labourers in his Vineyard, the Co-workers with him, and all other titles they claime, given in Scripture to the Apoſtles,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120014:20"/> though neither for their abilities, much leſſe for their vertues or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, or in any other reſpect can be due unto them.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The third intereſt is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the people, that the Scriptures though we have them in our owne tongue, are not yet to be underſtood by us without their helpe and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, ſo that in effect we are in the ſame condition with thoſe we have ſo long pitied, that are forbid to have the Scripturs in their own tongue: for 'tis all one not to have them in our own tongue, and to be made beleive, that we cannot underſtand them though we have them in our owne. Is the Cabinet open to us, and doe we yet want a Key? has ſo much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour been ſpent? ſo many Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons extant, and are we yet to ſeeke? Let us argue a little
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120014:20"/> with them: either the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not rightly Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or they are: If they are not, why have wee not beene told ſo all this while? why have wee beene cheated into errours? If they are rightly Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, why ſhould not Engliſhmen underſtand them? The Idiomes and properties of the Hebrew, and Greeke Languages, which ſome ſay, cannot word for word be expreſt in Engliſh, might all this while have beene Tranſlated into as many Engliſh words as will carry the ſence thereof. There is nothing in the Hebrew or Greeke but may be expreſt in Engliſh, though not juſt in ſo many words (which is not materiall) ſo that it muſt be confeſt, that either we have not beene fairly dealt withall hitherto in the conveyance of the Scripture,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120014:21"/> (a thing which few dare ſuſpect) or elſe the Scriptures are as well to be underſtood by us, as by any Linguiſt whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Well, notwithſtanding all this how evident ſoever it be, a great part of us people doe beleeve juſt as they would have vs, and therefore ſilly men (as we are) in caſe of doubt to them we goe to be reſolved: and hereby is maintained the neceſſity and excellency of learning, and the Languages, and ſo of Univerſities, and a ſuppoſall that the arts like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are of neceſſity to a Divine: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven yeares at leaſt are allotted for the attaining thereof, to fit and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe men for the ſtudy of Divinity, the Arts being, as they ſay, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maids and preparations to Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. But I heare wiſe men ſuſpect all this, and ſay, that the Divines of what ſort ſoever, have other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120014:21"/> ends in urging all theſe things to be of neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they have hereby made it a difficult thing to be a Miniſter, and ſo have engroſſed the trade to them ſelves, and left al other men by rcaſon of their other profeſſions in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity of being ſuch in their ſenſe.</p>
            <p>And therefore, Secondly, if any doe take upon them their profeſſion without Univerſity breeding and skill in the Arts and Languages (how knowing a man ſo ever he be otherwiſe) they have faſtened ſuch an <hi>odium</hi> in the hearts of moſt of the people againſt him, that a theif or murderer cannot be more out of their favour then he. Thirdly, they being furniſhed with theſe Arts and Languages, have a mighty advantage over all ſuch as have them not, &amp; care admirers therof, (as moſt men are) ſo that hereby they become maſters
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120014:22"/> of all diſcourſes, and can preſently ſtop the peoples mouthes, that put them too hard. to-it, by telling them that it is not for Lay-men to be too confident, being no ſchollers, &amp; igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Originall; That the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall hath it otherwiſe then our Tranſlations: And thus they keep al in a myſtery, that they only may bee the Oracles to diſpence what, &amp; how they pleaſe: ſo that this third in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is of much concernment to them.</p>
            <p>I know what the ſcruple of moſt men wilbe, in reading of this laſt par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticulars almoſt all wilbe the Divines Advocate for Learning, &amp; have him in great hate &amp; deriſion, that is an enemy thereto. For as <hi>Diana</hi> was, ſo is Learning thoſe <hi>Crafts-mens</hi> living &amp; the peoples goddeſſe. However, I will make no Apologie for my ſelfe, but deſire, that every man would give his reaſon ſcope, boldly to examine,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:120014:22"/> what it is, what good the World receives from it, whether the moſt learned, or unlearned men have been the troublers of the World. How preſumptfious and confident the learned Scribes, Prieſts, and Doctors of the Law were, that they beſt underſtood the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: How the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Fiſhermen and Tent-makers were made choyce of for Chriſts Diſciples and Apoſtles, before any of them: How in proceſſe of time they that tooke upon them to be Miniſters, when they had acquired to themſelves the myſterie of Arts and Learning, &amp; confounded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the cleare ſtreames of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and perver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the true Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, and by politicke Gloſſes, and Comments intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced an other Goſpell ſutable to the covetous, ambitious, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120014:23"/> perſecuting ſpirit of the Clergie (which their eſteeme with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made authentick) they then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſcorne the ſimplicity and meaneſſe of the Apoſtles, to call that the Infancy of the Church, and to engroſſe great Livings, Lordſhips, Territories and Dominions; to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyle States in warres, to ſupplant one an other and divert the people from the proſecution of their owne intereſt, (which is their ſafety and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie) to maintaine their quarrells, and erect that Government the then riſing part of them could agree upon. So that the Preiſts and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſtendome (though others have the name) yet they are indeed the Lords and leaders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as at preſent by Englands ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience may evidently appeare: For I would have all wiſe men conſider,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120014:23"/> ther the party who are now in armes to make us ſlaves, conſiſts not cheifly of ſuch as have had eſteeme for the moſt learned Arts men in the Kingdome; or of others, (who if not learned themſelves) are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of ſuch as are. Yea, to examine whence moſt of the warres of Chriſtendome have ſprung, and whether theſe artif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciall Clergie men have not been the cheife cauſers and ſtill are the grand Incendiaries of our preſent miſeries which threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten our utter ruine, and although the Epifcopall Clergie pretend to ſtrive for the Regall Prerogative on the one ſide, and the Presbiterian Prelacy for Reformation, and the Liberty of the Subject on the other ſide; yet both of theſe mainely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> their owne reſpective profits, and advancements; ſo that which ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de ſoever prevaile (if ſuch may
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120014:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:120014:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:120014:25"/> have their wills (both aiming at their own greatneſſe and Dominion over the conſciences of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) extreameſt miſerie, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt kind of ſlavery will unavoydably follow; whilſt each of them by all ſlye inſinuations and cunning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances ſeeke to obtaine authority to compell the whole Nation to be ſubject to their doubtfull, yea groundleſſe determinations, which of all other is the greateſt and worſt ſort of oppreſſion and tyranny. The people may, if they pleaſe, dote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which ever hath been, and will be their deſtruction: It would be more ſafe for them (I am ſure) to diſtinguiſh of Knowledge, and to reject what is uſeleſſe (as moſt of that which hath hitherto borne the name of learning, will upon impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall examination prove to be) and eſteeme that only which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120014:25"/> uſefull to the people; to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count better of them that having no by-ends or reſpects, have ſtudied the the Scriptures for their owne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers information, and doe impart the ſame to the people out of a deſire of their good, for nothing, (as the Anabaptiſts doe to their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) than of ſuch men as uſe all meanes to augment their tythes and profits, who being rich and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly provided for, yet exact them from poore poople, even ſuch whoſe very bellies can hardly ſpare it; whoſe neceſſities ought to be releeved by them, and not the fruite of their labours ſo unreaſonably wreſted from them, as oft it is, and the ſame ſo ſuperfluouſly ſpent, or ſo cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly hoarded up, as for the moſt part is knowne to be. When they commend Learning, it is not for Learnings ſake, but their owne; her
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:120014:26"/> eſteeme gets them their Livings and preferments; and therefore ſhe is to be kept up, or their Trade will goe downe. <hi>Have a care therefore O yee Clergie,, as you eſteem your honour and preferment, your profit and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, that you keep this Diana of yours high in the peoples eſteem: Rouze up your ſelves, and imagine ſome new wayes to quicken the admiration of this your Goddeſſe; for I can aſſure you, mens eyes begin to open, they find that ſhe is not ſo beautifull as ſhe once ſeemed to be; that her luſtre is not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, but painted and artificiall: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre your ſelves, or your Diana will downe.</hi> But why ſhould I excite you, who I know are too induſtrious in the preſervation of your owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts.</p>
            <p>Divers other intereſts they have plied, as to make themſelves the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publike ſpeakers, by which meanes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120014:26"/> whome, and what they pleaſe they openly condemne, cry up, or cry downe, what makes for or againſt themſelves: There they brand men with the name of Hereticks, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtren what errours they thinke are moſt hatefull to the people, upon thoſe men they purpoſe to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: There they confute all opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and boldly they may doe it, for as much as no liberty of reply or vindication in publike is allowed to any, though never ſo much ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized by them. And that men may not vindicate themſelves by writing, their next intereſt is to be Maſters of the Preſle, of which they are lately become by an Ordinance for licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Bookes, which being inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Parliament for a good &amp; neceſſary end (namely) the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of all Bookes dangerous or ſcandalous to the State, is become by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120014:27"/> meanes of the Licencers (who are Divines and intend their owne inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt) moſt ſerviceable to themſelves ſcandalous Books being ſtill diſperſt) in the ſtopping of honeſt mens wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that nothing may come to the Worlds view but what they pleaſe, unleſſc men will runne the hazard of impriſonment, (as I now doe) ſo that in publike they may ſpeake what they will, write what they wil, they may abuſe whom they will, and nothing can be ſaid againſt them: well may they preſume of making themſelves Maſters of the people ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving theſe foundations laid, and the people generally willing to beleive they are good. I might proceed, to ſhew what uſage wiſe men expect from their Government, being once eſtabliſht how rigid and auſtere ſome thinke they will prove, countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing no recreations but what them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120014:27"/> are addicted to: how cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous others deem them, obſerving that they have more regard to the Benefice then the people, and doe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually change and ſhift upon proffer of a better Parſonage. Some ſay that they are a people ſicke of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes diſeaſe, they love to ſit upermoſt at feafts, &amp; to be reverenced in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like places, that their reſpects to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men are as they are rich and benef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ciall to them, and that a pore man can hardly obtaine a viſite, though at the time when the world couceives there is greateſt neceſſity of it: that they'hover about dying men for their Fee, and hope of Legacy, &amp; many other things are commonly talked of them, which becauſe I ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be true I will ſet myſelf here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after more narrowly to obſerve.</p>
            <p>The Objection wereupon all this (I hope) neceſſary digreſſion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:120014:28"/> is built, was that men may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled (though again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> conſcience) to what the Synod or preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery ſhall conclude to be good, and agreable to Cods Word, becauſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and uniformity in the Church is to be endeavoured. To which I further</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Anſwer, That to ſorce men againſt their mind and judgment, to belecive what other men conclude to be true, would prove ſuch tyranny as the wicked <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> (mentioned by <hi>Plutarch)</hi> practiſed, who would fit all men to one Bed, by ſtretching them out that were too ſhort, and by cutting them ſhorter that were too long. If we beleive as the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod would have us, what is this but to be brought into their miſerable condition that muſt beleive as the Church beleives, and ſo become, (as ſaid an honeſt man, not the Diſciples
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120014:28"/> of Chriſt, but of the Synod?</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> The third Reaſon for Liberty of Conſcience is grounded upon theſe foundations, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not of faith is ſin, and that every man ought to be fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the trueneſſe of that way wherein he ſervcth the Lord: upon which grounds I thus argue, To compell me againſt my conſcience, is to compell me againſt what I beleive to be true, and ſo againſt my faith; now whatſoever is not of faith is ſin; To compell me therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my conſcience, is to compell me to doe that which is ſinfull: for though the thing may be in it ſelfe good, yet if it doe not appeare to be be ſo to my conſcience, the practice thereof in me is ſinfull, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ought not to be compelled unto.</p>
            <p>Againe I am counſelled by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120014:29"/> to be perſwaded in my owne mind of the truth of that way wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſerve the Lord; I am not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be compelled to worſhip God in ſuch a way, of the juſtneſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am not yet perſwaded, much leſſe in ſuch a way as is againſt my mind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Nothing is more dangerous to a State, eſpeacially in theſe times, than diviſion and diſturbance by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall wayes of Brethren which have encreaſed our miſeries, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoyde diviſion they who wil not of their own accords comply, are for the quiet of the ſtate to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled and puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I Anſwer, that it is verily thought that the harſhneſſe only of this propoſition hinders that it is not yet put in execution, till time &amp; cunning have fitted it for the people;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:120014:29"/> for we are told in the laſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion tending to diſwade from further gathering of Churches, that ſuffering is like to be the portion of ſuch as ſhall judge the right rule not to be delivered to them. A man would thinke that thoſe people that ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were the ſufferers, the noyſe of whoſe exclamations againſt ſuch courſes, is ſcarce yet ont of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples eares, that they ſhould not ſo ſoone thinke of being the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants. But to the Objection I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the diverſity of mens judgments is not the occaſion of diviſion, becauſe the word divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath reference to falling off from the Common cauſe. Now, though the provocations and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citements, againſt the Browniſts, and Anabaptiſts and ſome of the Independents have beene many, yet their affections to the Publike
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120014:30"/> weale are ſo hearty in them, and grounded upon ſuch ſound princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of reaſon, that no aſſay of the Synod can make them ceaſe to love and aſſiſt their Countrey; and it is more then evident by the proſperity of our neighbours in Holland, that the ſeverall wayes of our brethren in matters of Religion hinder not, but that they may live peaceably one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt an other, and the Spaniard will witneſſe for them that they u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſufficiently in the defence of their common liberties and oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their common enemies: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſids, its very materiall to conſider, that it hath ever been the practice of thoſe that are countenanced by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to endeavor the ſuppreſſion of thoſe that are not: who is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the fault? the quiet Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, who being perſwaded in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the truth of that way he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120014:30"/> deſires to ſerve the Lord in, peecea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly goes on to do his duty as he thinkes himſelfe bound to doe, or they who out of a lordly diſpoſition care not what injury they doe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though to the hazard of the Common-wealth, to advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their government, they defame the Separation in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and Sermons, bid their poſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites beware of them, as of a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and factious people, ſtoppe their mouthes, keep the Preſſe fom them, provoake them by all wayes poſſible, and then like the crafty Politian cry out upon them as the cauſers of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion.</p>
            <p>I heare ſome men ſay, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the Miniſter ſo to doe, becauſe his living (depending upon his tythes and guifts) is the greater, the more rich and numerous his audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is; and therefore the Separa iſts
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:120014:31"/> are not to be ſuffered, who they find by experience draw many people af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, and though not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout honourable women, nor the cheife men of the City, yet many whoſe number might much encreaſe the yearly revennue of the Miniſter, and therefore you muſt thinke it has concerned them to meet together, and to ſay amongſt themſelves,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sirs, you know that by this our craft we have our wealth: moreover ye ſe &amp; hear, that not alone at London, but in moſt parts of the Kingdom theſe Separatiſts have perſwaded &amp; turnd away much peo ple, ſaying that our Miniſtry is no true Miniſtry, our Church, no true Church, our Doctrine in many things erronious, that our ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles is but a pretended thing, &amp; as we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves do derive it deſcended for many 100. yeares through the deteſtable Papacy &amp;</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:120014:31"/> 
               <hi>miſh Miniſtry, ſo that if theſe men be ſuffered our gaine, and the magnificence of the Miniſtery, wich not England only, but all Chriſtendome doth high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly magnificence of the Miniſtery, wich not England only, but all Chriſtendome doth high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly magnifie and reverence, would quickly downe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For what other reaſon then this can be imagined, why the Separati on ſhould bee the eye-ſore of our Miniſters? It cannot be inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in one particular whereby the Common-wealth receives prejudice from them: And then for the charge of Separating, for their maknig a Sciſme, which is endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, to be caſt ſo heavily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them:</p>
            <p>I anſwer, That by reaſon of the Church of Romes corruptions, the Church of England did long ſince make a Sciſme from the Church of Rome, for
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120014:32"/> which cauſe likewiſe many of the preſent Miniſters in lieve of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian domineering Biſhops thought it no robbery to make ſciſme from England; and even this Idolizing Synod, which though not yet upon her Throne, ſticks not to let her clients ſee <hi>ſhe ſayes in her heart; Behold I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t a queen, I am no widdow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow, Rev. 18. 7.</hi> May not I ſay this, Reverend Synod: if to be proceeded againſt by ſuch carnall ſandy prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, ſuch humane ordinances, by which the Separatiſts ſtand preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced, be legally found, to have made the greateſt and moſt tranſcendent ſciſme which England ever knew or heard of, ſince the Papiſtrie was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded; If then the Separation have gon a little further, and not only with the Biſhops ſeparated from Rome, with the Miniſters from the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120014:32"/> Biſhops, but by reaſon of ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions ſtill remaining among the Miniſters, are by their conſciences necſſitated to ſeparate from them likewiſe: In all theſe ſeparations there was difference in judgment; the Biſhops differ in ſome things from Rome, our Miniſters from the Biſhops, and amongſt themſelves too, which differecnes by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they cannot determine, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth both by their writings and preachings, wherein with nuch ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency they urge the ſame againſt other; of little force then will the major vote of a Synod be for the determining thereof, having ſo lately moſt notoriouſly diſcovered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be men-pleaſers and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſers, by crying downe the things which but yeſterday they ſo highly magnified in their Pulpits, and alſo practiſed with much devotion (at
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120014:33"/> leaſt ſeemingly) and having withall their owne intereſts ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein (as is before in Part declared.) And further, knowing that the ſame perſons themſelves, and their Tenets, (as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of Independents, Browniſts, and Anababtiſts, whom they oppoſe) doe ſtand condemned not by the major vote of divers Synods only, but by many generall Counſells alſo, (who are accounted to repreſent the whole Church upon Earth) no whit inferiour to them either in Arts or Learning, or any other qualification: Let it be then no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor ſo much as ſeem blameable hereafter, that the Separatiſts ſhould differ in ſome Opinions from this preſent Synod, ſince the Miniſters therein no little differ amongſt them ſelves, much more than ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> appeares, and will do ſo, while Sun and Moon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120014:33"/> endures untill we have courage and ſtrength enough to abandon all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts and advantages.</p>
            <p>All times have produced men of ſeverall wayes, and I beleive no man thinkes there will be an agreement of judgement as longe as this World laſts: If ever there be, in all probability it muſt proceed from the power and efficacie of Truth, not from conſtraint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Objection.</hi> An Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, men that have imployed all their time in the ſtudy of Religion, are more likely to find out the truth, then other men, that have not ſo ſpent their time; who being now conſulting, what Doctrines, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:120014:34"/> what Diſcipline is moſt agreeable to the Word of God, it is but meet that all men ſhould waite their leaſure, till it be manifeſt what they ſhall produce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this objection I ſay firſt, That they being now in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation, not for themſelves, but as they ſay, for the whole people; it is but reaſonable that they ſhould pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to the world whatſoever is in debate amongſt them, and invite e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to give them their beſt light and information, that ſo they may heare all voyces, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ought againſt mens judgments before it be heard what they can ſay for themſelves: This might perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture be a meanes to find out all truth, and ſettle things ſo as that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man might be ſatisfied. You will ſay, that they conſider of all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:120014:34"/> objections amongſt themſelves. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that is not ſufficient, for 'tis a knowne caſe men are generally par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall to themſelves and their owne judgments, urging the weakeſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and that but ſlightly: and it can give no ſatisfaction to men to have their cauſes pleaded by their Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>Secondly, how palpable ſoever it appeare, that an Aſſembly of Divines are more likely to find out truth then other men; yet it is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that it will puzzle any man to inſtance when they did ſo. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, grant it be more probable, yet it may be otherwiſe, and 'tis well knowne hath proved ſo. The Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie was by univerſall conſent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and by the Parliaments Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority authoriſed, particular men being for theſe many yeares averſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:120014:35"/> to it, and ſeparating from the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Congregations becauſe of it: it now appeares who were in the right. How confident ſoever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Divines (as they ſtyle them ſelves) are that they ſhall find out the right rule; yet ſince it may be, and hitherto hath been otherwiſe, it is but meet that they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree only for themſelves and ſuch as are of their owne mind, and allow Chriſtian Liberty to all their Brethren to follow that way which ſhall ſeem to them moſt agreable to truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But we are told in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines Conſiderations that all men muſt wait, otherwiſe the Parliament are like to be provoaked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> J marry Sir, this is a good ſtrongue Argument, and ſpeakes home to us: I cannot blame the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:120014:35"/> Separatiſts now for crying out, they feare your Club more then your Reaſon. I ſee what they might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, if the ſword and authority were in your hand, your nine Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions informes me, wherin are theſe two ſuppoſitions. Firſt, <hi>that the right rule may not be delivered us:</hi> And ſecondly, <hi>that then men may be called to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffer.</hi> It is a wonder to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the wrethed condition of man, and his foule ingratitude: Is it ſo long ſince the yoakes were broaken off theſe mens necks, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the burthen &amp; injuſtice of them, or that aſſiſtance they had from their ſeparatiſt Brethren in breaking thoſe yoakes, that now ſo ſoone as they are got into reputation, they ſhould ſuppoſe a time of ſuffering for their brethren for doing what to them appeares to be their duty! <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard O God, ſince man is become thus</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:120014:36"/> 
               <hi>forgetfull, take thy diſtreſſed Servants, the Separatiſts into thine owne pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Thou O Lord, that art the Judge of all the Earth, put into the hearts of the Parliament to doe right in this cauſe, and to ſuffer thoſe afflicted people no longer to endure reproach or moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for doing of their duties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ob. But ſome may I beat the Aire all this while, there is no purpoſe in the Divines to force the conſcience, they are ſufficienily informed that, the conſcience cannot be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, being in no wiſe ſnbject to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, only it concerues them they ſay to prevent the grouth and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of errours, which cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be done but by puniſhing thoſe that are the authors and maintainers of them, that ſo truth only may flouriſh, and the Goſpell with the Ordinances according to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:120014:36"/> the true inſtitution of them, be maintained and practiſed by all the people of the Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, that though it were certaine that what they eſteeme truth were ſo indeed, and that the true Goſpell and Ordinances were in every part and circumſtance of them that which they judge them to be: however, though they are earneſtly to endeavour by argument and perſwation to reduce all men to the ſame beleife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and practice with themſelves, yet thoſe that cannot be thereunto periwaded, they ought not by any meanes to puniſh, for the firſt and third Reaſons afore given. But then for the aſſurance of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines that their concluſions and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are certainly true, if it be built vpon certaine foundations, they need not avoyde the combate with any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:120014:37"/> ſort of men of what opinion ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: Truth was uot uſed to feare, or to ſeeke ſhifts or ſtratagems for its advancement! I ſhould rather thinke that they who are aſſured of her ſhould deſire that all mens mouthes ſhould be open, that ſo errour may diſcover its foulnes and trueth become more glorious by a victorious conqueſt after a fight in open field; they ſhunne the battell that doubt their ſtrenght. Wiſe men are at a ſtand to ſee that whileſt the Preſſe was open no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke the Anabaptiſts, and that now their adverſaries have bound their hands they begin to buffet them; what can they doe elſe but neceſſarily ſſupect that our Divines have not the truth, nor by any evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thereof are able to make good their owne ſtandings or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices. To ſtop mens mouths or
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:120014:37"/> puniſh men for ſpeaking their mindes, was profitable indeed, and neceſſarie for the Biſhopes who had propoſed to themſelves ſuch endes as could endure no diſcourſe upon them, and framed ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, ceremonies and doctrines, as muſt be received without ſcanning, or elſe would appeare empty and groundleſſe. But that the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Clergy, that pretend to have truth in its ſimplicity, and the Goſpell in its purity, and ſeeme to abominate all by-endes or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, ſhould yet take the ſame courſe of prohititions with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, locke up the Preſſe, and then vent themſelves in a furious and (evidently) ſcandalizing way, as in their late preachings and Pamphlets againſt the Anabaptiſts, will make, I beleeve, all wiſe men ſuſpect that either they doubt their
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:120014:38"/> owne tenets, or know ſome groſſe errours amongſt themſelves, which yet their intereſts and profeſſions engage them to maintaine. To ſay they goe not about to compell the conſcience, which is uncapable of compu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion, but will only puniſh the perſon, is as if they were ſportfull in their cruelty, and ſhewes as if it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from men ſetled, and long practiſed in tyranny, I could wiſh for Chriſtianity ſake they had more wiſedome then to play with mens afflictions: I profeſſe unto you, did I ſtill dote upon the perſons and ſeeming holyneſſe of our Miuiſters (as I have done) ſuch carriage as this I thinke would open mine eyes, and make me ſee they are not the men they ſeeme to be, that in ſo ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time can grow ſo wanton with their owne eſtate and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, as to gibe and ſcoffe at their brethrens miſeries. Is it not a ſhame
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:120014:38"/> to our profeſſion, and ſcandall to our cauſe, that well affected men, reall, and irreconcileable enemies to tyranny, and our common Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, ſhould be neceſſitatd to leave their native Country, becauſe they can hope nothing from you, our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, but to be impriſoned or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for exerciſing their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though by their helpe you ſhould be ſetled in your liberties, I cannot tell what elſe to make of this for my part, but that <hi>you bad rather be ſlaves to the King, and hazard the freed me of the whole Nation, then that theſe men ſhould have freedome with you;</hi> yee may flatter your ſelves, that yee are rich in ſpirituall graces, and preſume that you are in the right, and have found out the truth of the Goſpell and Ordieances, but ſo long as yee want the maine evidences thereof, <hi>Love and lowlineſſe of mind,</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:120014:39"/> ſo long as yee propoſe dominion and the ſway over your Brethren, which our Saviour ſaid his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhonld not doe, <hi>Matth. 20. 25. 26. Murke 10. 42.</hi> you muſt give men that are unwilling to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved leave to thinke that yee have yet but the forme and ſhew of Religion, but want the inward ſweetneſſe and moſt excellent fruites and effects thereof; I could wiſh I had no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for ſpeaking thus much, but when ſores bigin to feſter, they muſt not be nouriſhed and ſwathed, but lanc'd and corraciv'd, 'tis no time to hide and excuſe mens imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when they ſtrive to take roote for perpetuity. Were it in mine own cauſe, I could not ſpeak ſo much, but in halfe of ſuch a harmeleſſe people as I have found thoſe of the Separation to be, after much inquiry and examination of their Tenets,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:120014:39"/> and practice, I thinke my ſelfe bound in conſcience to breke ſilence and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their advocate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> There is one Objection more againſt the Anabaptiſts in particular, and that is, that they allow not of Civill government and therefore not to be tolerated becauſe they hold an opinion directly deſtructive to the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Who ſaies they hold this opinion? why the Divines common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Pulpits, and what ground have they for their ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? They find it in bookes that they who have written of them affirme that they maintaine this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. But how if the ſocieties of Anabaptiſts in this Kinghome are moſt Zealous and rationall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of our Government? as to my knowledge they are, and that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:120014:40"/> experience can teſtifie for them, that noe men have more forwardly and conſtantly then they aſſiſted the Parliament againſt thoſe that would diſolve our free governement, and bring in tyranny; how is it true then that the Anabaptiſts hold ſuch an opinion? O then they tell us that our Anabaptiſts are no Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts: To what purpoſe then doe they exclaime againſt Anabaptiſts that have been of that opinion? (as they ſay) (though for my part I beleeve neither them, nor the books that tells them ſo) when they cannot but know, if they know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that the Anabaptiſts which now are, be not of that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; why for this end and purpoſe, they reſolve to make the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts odious to the people, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they thinke will ſooner doe it, then by making the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:120014:40"/> that they are the harbourers of ſuch an opinion as would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all ſocietie, and bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to confuſion the ſtate.</p>
            <p>Now this they ſpeake of the Anabaptiſts in generall, knowing that the people will apply it to the Anabaptiſts in England, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom how true it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you may judge by that which followes.</p>
            <p>The Anabaptiſts opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Government is, that the world being growne ſo vitious, and corrupt as it is, there can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be no living for honeſt men without Government: That the end of making Government, is the Peoples quiet and ſafety, and that whatſoever doth not conduce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is tyranny or oppreſſion &amp; not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120014:41"/> That the Government of England is of all others that they know the moſt excellent, the people by their choſen men, being the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers &amp; reformers therof: That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Parliament is the ſupreme po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and that the King is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them for the not perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his Office, as all other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Common-wealth are: That the Parliament only are the makers and alterers of Lawes for the regulation and ordering of the people: That of right they are to be called by thoſe Lawes they have made in that behalfe, and to diſſolve when they themſelves ſee good: that it is not at the Kings wil or pleaſure to ſigne or refuſe thoſe Bills the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament ſhall paſſe, but that he is of duty to ſigne them: That all great Officers and Majeſtrates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are to be choſen by them:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:120014:41"/> That the King is to have his perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall abode neer the Parliament, that they may have free conference with him at pleaſure touching the former diſcharge of his Office, or the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of the Common-wealth: That to Parliaments alone belong the diſpoſall of Shipping, Forts, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, and all other the Kingdomes ſtrengths, both by Sea &amp; Land: The making of peace &amp; war, the preſſing of ſouldiers, the raiſing of monie for the preſerving or regaining the ſafety or freedome of the people, which for any other perſon to doe, is treaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Theſe grounds &amp; principles of our government they knowing, could not but ſee the exorbitances of the King, &amp; whereto al his lawles courſes &amp; deſignes tended, &amp; therefore have not ignorantly (as perhaps others) but upon theſe grounds aſſiſted the Parliament, and will doe till the laſt.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:120014:42"/>
            <p>Judge by this then whether theſe men hold an opinion againſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or at what wretchleſſe paſſe thoſe men are that would make the people beleive they doe.</p>
            <p>I might inſiſt here upon a Booke called <hi>The Confutation of Anabaptiſts</hi> lately ſet forth, which ſaies, <hi>They are abſolute and profeſſed enemies to the eſſentiall Being of Civill Government,</hi> but I find people ſo little regard the Booke, it being ſo full of non-ſence, and in this particular ſo evidently contrary to truth, and the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of every man, that lookes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and knowes any thing of the Anabaptiſts; that it will be but loſſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time to take notice of it, only it were worth obſervation to ſee how eaſily it obtained an <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> and how open the Preſſe is to any thing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:120014:42"/> true or falſe, ſence or non-ſence, that tends to the Anabaptiſts ſcandall or diſgrace.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a Booke was publiſhed, called the Hiſtory of the Anabaptiſts in High and Low Germany, the aime whereof was by faſtning odious errours and feigned mutenies upon the Anabaptiſts to deter this preſent Parliament in their Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Biſhops, for feare, as the booke ſaies, leaſt they who now cry out for Chriſts rule, ſtrike not ſo much at the miſrule of Epiſcopacy, as quarrell at all rules, ſo that what courſe was taken by the Biſhops and their freinds to hinder the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of that Hierarchie, namely, the affrighting the Reformers by airy and imaginary conſequences, the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:120014:43"/> ſame are uſed by our Divines to prevent a through Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; of many erroures, and miſtakes in our Clergie, which they exceedingly feare, and therefore they have, and doe continue early and late to render the Anabaptiſts as odious to the people as their wits and inventions can make them. But as the Biſhops then failed of their ends by the wiſedome of the Parliament; ſo I truſt the preſent endeavoures of our Divines in ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to raiſe themſelves upon their Brethrens diſgrace and ruine, will by the continued courage and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Parliament prove vaine and fruitleſſe.</p>
            <p>They who eccho the Kings words and take the Biſhops courſe (I will not ſay have the Kings ends but) ſo farre doe the Kings worke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:120014:43"/>
            <p>The King, I confeſſe, has reaſon to cry out upon the Aabaptiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knowes them to be enemies not of Government, but oppreſſion in Government, and all thoſe who intend to oppreſſe in any manner, ought, if they will be true to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to doe ſo too; for the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts are oppreſſions enemies, whoever be the oppreſſours.</p>
            <p>And whereas they ſay, they find in Bookes, that the Anabaptiſts are enemies to all Government, it were well if they would confider who wrote thoſe Bookes: it may be they were written either by miſtake, or for the ſame end ahat they repeate them. We can ſhew you books too, that ſay the Parliament are Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts &amp; Anabaptiſts; And paſt all queſtion, if the King ſhould thrive in this unnaturall warre, this Parl.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:120014:44"/> ſhould in their Court Hiſtories, not only be called Anabaptiſts, but bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo to all poſterity with that opinion falſly and maliciouſly fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the Anabaptiſts, That they were enemies to Government, and went about to bring all into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. little credite therefore is to given to Bookes in matter of oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie and ſcandall: but the men, and their judgments in the times they live, are to be conſidered: And then I am confident it will appeare, that the Anabaptiſts be of well affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted mindes, and peaceable diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, meriting a faire reſpect from the State, and may well challenge amongſt others, the quiet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of themſelves as they are men, and the ordinances of Chriſt as they are Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>I will adde one thing more to the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:120014:44"/> Browniſts and Anabaptiſts glory; that in the times of the Biſhops do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering, when many of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians complyed, ſome to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry top of <hi>Wrens</hi> Conformity, and preached for thoſe things they now prerend cheifly to reforme, and the Independants fled to places where they might live at eaſe, and enjoy their hundred pounds a yeare, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger; the Browniſt and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt endured the heate and brunt of perſecution, and notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſeverall wayes of vexing them, continued doing their duties, counting it the glory of a Chriſtian to endure tribulation for the name of Chriſt: And the times a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the Presbyterian ſoon comes about, and the Independant comes over, to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaders in the Reformation, when forgetting the conſtancie and integrity of thoſe who bore the heat
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:120014:45"/> and burden of the day, they hold the ſame heavy hand over them, that their fathers the Biſhops did. And as the Browniſts &amp; Anabaptiſts affection to the common good of all, was themfirme, &amp; able to endure the triall of perſccution, ſo hath it in theſe preſent ſearching times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued conſtant &amp; unſhaken, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the many almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable Injuries &amp; provocations of the Divines on the one fide, &amp; the faire promiſes &amp; frequent invitations of the King on the other; ſo that had any ends of their owne beene aimed at, they could not have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſuch reſolved &amp; immoveable enemies of Tyranny, &amp; freinds to their conutry: I beleeve if we would ſuppoſe other men to be in their Condition, we could hardly expect the like even &amp; upright carriage from them, amidſt ſo many ſtormes and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:120014:45"/> temptations ſurrounding them. I hope all good men will take all that hath been ſaid into conſideration, eſpecially the Parliament who I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume are moſt ingenuous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall of all others. and whom it cheifly concernes, they being called and truſted to vindicate and preſerve the peoples liberties in generall, and not to enthrall the Conſciences, Perſons, or Eſtates of any of them unto a pregmaticall pretended Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, whether Epiſcopall, Presbiteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or any other whatſoever, The greateſt glory of authority is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the diſtreſſed; and for thoſe that are Judges in other mens cauſes to beare themſelves as if the afficted mens caſes were their owne; obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that divine rule of our Saviour, <hi>What ſoever yee would that usen ſhould due vnto you, even ſo doe yee to them</hi> And if to the Parl. it ſhall appeare for the reaſons given or other better
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:120014:46"/> they can ſiggeſt to themſelves, that it is moſt uniuſt, and much more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, that any man ſhould be compelied againſt his conſcience to a way he approves not of, I doubt not but they wilbe pleaſed for Gods glory, and vnion ſake and likewiſe for theſe good mens ſake, which for the preſent it principally concernes, at leaſt for their owne ſakes (for who knowes how ſocne this may be his owne caſe) ſpeedily to ſtop all proceedings that tends thereunto: and for the future provide, that as well particular or private Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, as publike, may have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like protection, ſo that upon a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty no injury or offence be offered either to them from others, or by them to others. That all Statutes againſt the Separatiſts be reviewed, and repealed, eſpecially that of the 35. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> That the Preſſe may be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:120014:46"/> free for any man, that writes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtandalous or dangerous to the State. That ſo this Parliament may prove themſelves loving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to all ſorts of good men, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring equall reſpect to all, according to the truſt repoſed in them, and ſo inviting an equall affection and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from all: that after Ages may report of them, they did all theſe things, not becauſe of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of the people, or to pleaſe a party, but from the reaſon and juſtneſſe of them, which did more ſway with them, then a Petition ſubſcribed with Twenty thouſand hands could have done.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
